Finding Aid for Reginald F. Sharkey papers, 1953-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Reginald F. Sharkey papers 1953-2007, 1967-1991
Sharkey, Reginald, 1913-2005.
1 oversize folders
4.5 linear feet (in 6 boxes)
2009159 Aa2; UAl
Conservationist from Petoskey, Michigan who wrote columns and served as an environmental reporter for several regional newspapers; records include published newspaper columns and articles, drafts, photographs and negatives, and documentation relating to his conservation work.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the Little Traverse Historical Society through Betty Reddig (donor no. 9338 ) in 2009.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Born in Big Rapids, Michigan in 1913, Reginald Sharkey served in World War II and as an aviator until 1964 when he began work with the Michigan Department of Conservation, now the Department of Natural Resources. He specialized in Petoskey-area fisheries. During the late-sixties, Sharkey became an environmental reporter and columnist for several papers in Northern Michigan, including the Petoskey News-Review and the Charlevoix County Press. In 1997, at the age of 83, he published The Blue Meteor: The Tragic Story of the Passenger Pigeon with the Little Traverse Historical Society.
The Reginald Sharkey collection consists of three series: Conservation Career, Writing Career, and Visual Materials. The collection's strength lies in drafts of Sharkey's columns, photographs, and drawings related to wildlife and the environment in Northern Michigan in the 1970s and 1980s.
Subjects:
Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Oral histories.; Outdoor writers--Michigan.; Petoskey (Mich.); Sharkey, Reginald, 1913-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Environmental policy--Michigan.; Sharkey, Reginald, 1913-; Wildlife conservation--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Drawings (visual works); Editorial cartoons.; Photographs.
- Conservation Career
  The Conservation Career series documents Sharkey's activities as a conservationist for the DNR, as well as his conservation-related activities in the Petoskey community.
  - Newspaper articles about Reginald Sharkey 1971-1985 (Box 1)
  - Bird Banding Certificates 1970-1977 (Box 1)
  - Bird Drawings and Prints undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1968-1975 (Box 1)
  - Disposition of Reginald Sharkey Papers (Box 1)
  - "Feeding Behavior of the American Merganser in Captivity," The Journal of Wildlife Management, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Transcript of Oral History Interview with Reginald Sharkey 2004; also other related biographical information, 2005-2007 (Box 1)
  - PCB Contamination 1975 (Box 1)
- Writing Career
  The Writing Career series documents Sharkey's writing activities. Materials in this series primarily include copies of his columns, photographs, and articles for Harbor Light, the Petoskey News-Review, The Graphic, the Charlevoix County Press, and the Traverse City Eagle Record. The drafts for many of his columns are also in this series, as well as materials relating to magazine articles that Sharkey either published or submitted for publication with Outdoor Life.
  - Book Proposal 2001, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Magazine Articles
    - "Persian Boar Blitz," Article Draft 1953 (Box 1)
    - "The Big Mac Bear," Outdoor Life, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Columns
    - Drafts
      - 1970s, 4 folders (Box 1)
      - 1980s (Box 1)
    - Published
      - "Emmet Soil Conservation Edition," Supplement to Petoskey News-Review, 1976-1981 (Box 1)
      - "Jackpine Journal," Petoskey News-Review, 1972-1979, 8 folders (Box 1)
      - "Jackpine Journal," Petoskey News-Review, 1980-1990, 9 folders (Box 2)
      - "Nature Along the Way," Harbor Light, 1967-1971, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - "Reg Sharkey's Northern Journal," Charlevoix County Press, 1988-1991, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Reporting
    - Harbor Light, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Natural Resources Register, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Petoskey News-Review, 1972-1988, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - The Graphic, 1983-1987 (Box 2)
    - Traverse City Record-Eagle, 1990 (Box 2)
- Visual Materials
  The final series Visual Materials is comprised of pen and ink drawings, photographs, negatives, and contact sheets on nature-related themes. The bulk of the material consists of negatives and contact sheets of local wildlife.
  - Original Drawings
    - Illustration of Civil War cannon (Box 3)
    - Editorial Cartoons (Box 3)
      (danger of pesticides to fish and wildlife, problem of solid waste disposal, etc.)
    - Prints and slides of some of his illustrations and drawings (Box 3)
    - Wildlife Illustrations: Birds, Fish, Insects, Rabbits, Rodents, and Weasels, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous subjects (Box 3)
    - Editorial Cartoons and other illustrations, 16 items (Box 6)
      (environmental policy and wildlife)
    - Editorial Cartoons
      - "Duel of Death" featuring bear and hunter (Folder 1)
      - Overpopulation (Folder 1)
      - "Mt. Trashmore" (Folder 1)
      - "King Oil and Company" and the Pigeon River Country State Forest (Folder 1)
    - Wildlife Illustrations
      - Fox and mountain lion eyeing a rabbit (Folder 1)
  - Photographs
    - Buildings: Church, Houses, Lighthouses, and Outhouse (Box 4)
    - Nature Scenes: Winter, wetlands, etc. (Box 4)
    - People: Archery, ice fishing, photoprints of historical logging camps, group and individual portraits, and miscellaneous activities (Box 4)
    - Transportation: Airplane, sail and motor boats, and train (Box 4)
    - Wildlife: Birds, Deer, Fish, Insects, Raccoons, Reptiles, and Rodents, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Negatives and Contact Sheets
    - Undated, 13 folders (Box 4)
    - 1974-1978, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1980-1988, 13 folders (Box 5)